karlhillx@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/khill

SOFTWARE ENGINEER WITH LEADERSHIP STRENGTHS

SUMMARY

Software Engineer and Architect with over 25 years of experience in executing the software development lifecycle (SDLC) in agile, consumer-facing environments. Has a demonstrated history of implementing complex projects, exceeding customer expectations, and achieving aggressive goals. Built positive relationships across business functions to drive development, increasing functionality, usability, and accessibility of products while reducing design, development, and maintenance costs.

EXPERIENCE

SENIOR FULL STACK ENGINEER, NASA, 2017 - Present, Science Systems and Applications, Inc. (SSAI), Greenbelt, MD

- Built an automated content registry application for NASA Earth Observatory that crawls NASA domains to discover new online earth science content enriching internal data and increasing research efficiency by over 50%.
- Overhauled award-winning website, earthobservatory.nasa.gov, a high-traffic site with roughly 1.5 million monthly hits;
 streamlined site for improved performance, usability, user experience, and overall SEO.
- Spearheaded redevelopment of internal admin systems used by 15 employees, improving functionality/reliability by 20%.
- Authored business requirements for a NASA Direct Readout Laboratory application, led requirements elicitation sessions, solution assessment, use cases, and interface/functionality mock-ups (predicted lowered TTM by over six months).

LARAVEL DEVELOPER, 2016 – 2017, InformedDNA, St. Petersburg, FL

- Coded and architected a case management application for medical professionals, resulting in better usability, cut runtime performance by 50% of the previous application, and saving roughly \$35K in UX/UI work.
- Increased use with the new application by more than 35%; eliminated the need for three DB instances using custom APIs.
- Led development of features for the company's CRM system, accelerated revenues by 15%.
- Coordinated upgrades and maintenance to ensure security, including patching and backups, to avert downtime costs.

SENIOR CONSULTANT, 2012 – 2015, Ticomix, Inc., Washington, DC

- Implemented custom CRM applications for over 20 clients, including VDOT (Virginia Department of Transportation),
 Washington Redskins, and Kastle Systems, providing advanced functionality for new/existing features and amplifying sales.
- Reduced defect backlog from hundreds to 25 at launch, improving product quality while maintaining a high customer satisfaction rating and reducing support costs for a top-tier client.
- Created application to help companies identify qualified business opportunities, saving thousands vs. alternative solutions.

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER, 2010 - 2012, Sabre Corporation, Bethesda, MD

- Developed and enhanced applications in a fast-paced environment, meeting performance and reliability for five of the largest global airline, hotel, and travel agency clients (improved customer satisfaction scores by 20%).
- Liaised with marketing to drive email and social media advertising, using modeling, resulting in a 15% increase in revenue.
- Mentored three junior developers and new hires, helping them grow professionally (received promotions within a year).

Additional roles include **Senior Software Engineer** for **Verizon**, **Dante Inc**, **Visitar**, and **Advantage Industries**, plus current volunteer developer positions at **Friendship Place** and **The Renwick Gallery of the Smithsonian American Art Museum**.

EDUCATION

Certificate in Project Management - Rutgers University, Camden, NJ

Bachelor of Science (B.S.), Computer Science coursework - University of Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD

Associate of Arts (A.A.), General Studies - Howard Community College, Columbia, MD

SKILLS

Laravel, PHP, PHPUnit, TDD, Apache, Tomcat, LAMP, MySQL, MariaDB, PostgreSQL, MVC, Symfony, Webpack, NPM, OOP, HTML5, CSS3, SASS, JavaScript, jQuery, Vue.js, Bootstrap, Tailwind, Git, GitHub/GitLab, Subversion SVN, APIs, REST, JSON, UX/UI, Agile, Scrum, Java, JSF, SugarCRM, WordPress, Drupal, Apache Nutch, ElasticSearch, AWS (Amazon Web Services), Atlassian Suite: (JIRA, Confluence, Bitbucket), Composer, Bash & Shell scripting